Partial Guide to the Memorial Library of Music Collection
Department of Special Collections
Memorial Library of Music collection
MLM
Keating, George T.
ca. 27 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
This library is a collection of musical manuscripts and of printed and engraved scores inscribed by great composers, and constitutes a unique addition to Stanford's educational and cultural resources.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from Memorial Library of Music, 1993.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Memorial Library of Music at Stanford University has been made possible by the interest and generosity of Mr. and Mrs. George T. Keating and the painstaking and devoted efforts of Professor Nathan van Patten.
The Memorial Library of Music has quite fittingly been conceived as a part of Stanford's memorial to her honored alumni who gave their lives in World War II. Their sacrifice has also been marked by the establishment of the University's Gold Star Scholarships for their children and by engraving their names forever on the Roll of Honor in beautiful Memorial Hall. The completion of this first volume of the catalogue affords occasion to express the University's deep appreciation of the contribution which Mr. and Mrs. Keating have made.
J.E. Wallace Sterling November 8, 1950.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Barzun, Jacques, 1907-; Friedrich, Goetz.; Keating, George T., b. 1892; Litvinov, Maxim; Menotti, Gian Carlo, 1911-; Milhaud, Darius, 1892-1974.; Montenezzi, Italo.; Rachmaninoff, Sergei; Ritchie, Ward, 1905-; Rodgers, Richard, 1902-; Sandberg, Mordecai.; Schatzki, Walter.; Schulhof, Andrew.; Schwarz, Kurt.; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965.; Shostakovich, Dmitri*i Dmitrievich, 1906-1975.; Sibelius, Jean, 1865-1957.; Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949.; Stravinsky, Igor, 1882-1971.; Thompson, Virgil.; Valle, Rafael Heliodoro, 1891-1959.; Winternitz, Emanuel.; Stechert-Hafner, Inc.; Memorial Library of Music.; Music.
Collection Contents
- Chant de victoire à Jeanne d'Arc-paroles d'Alph. / ADAM, ADOLPHE CHARLES (1803-1856), MLM 1
  Garalle. Mus. d' Ad. Adam. Original manuscript signed. March 30, 1855. 2 leaves (4 pages) 34 1/2 x 27 cm. Original manuscript of the text by Alphonse Garalle (cf. separate entry). (see #351)
- Giralda ou la nouvelle Psyche. / ADAM, ADOLPHE CHARLES (1803-1856), MLM 2
  "Opéra comique en trois actes, paroles de Mr. E. Scribe; musique de Ad. Adam.. Paris, Brandus [1850] P1. no. 5301. First edition. Inscribed to Pierre Joseph Guillaume Zimmerman by the composer. Orchestral score. Presented for the first time at Paris, July 20, 1850. Wotquenne, 1323.
- [Autographed signed letter] / ADAM, ADOLPHE CHARLES (1803-1856), MLM 2A.
  "Inserted is an autograph letter signed. To an unidentified correspondent, n. p.,n.d.
- Le postillon de Longjumeau. / ADAM, ADOLPHE CHARLES (1803-1856), MLM 3
  "Opéra comique en trois actes. Paroles de... MM. de Leuven et Brunswick. Musique de Ad. Adam. Partition piano et chant. Paris, G. Brandus et S. Dufour [ca. 1855] P1. no. M. S. 5189. At head of title: ""Nouvelle edition."" Presented for the first time at Paris, October I 2, 1836. Wotquenne, 2510. Manuscript in Adam's hand of Alcindor's Air, no. 7 (cf. separate entry). (Not inserted).
- "[Le postillon de Longjumeau] Alcindor's Air, no. 7. " / ADAM, ADOLPHE CHARLES (1803-1856), MLM 4
  "Original manuscript. ca. 1836. 2 leaves (3 pages) 341/2 X 26cm. In the ""Nouvelle edition"" of the piano and vocal score.
- Le Roi des Halles / ADAM, ADOLPHE CHARLES (1803-1856), MLM 4A.
- Le roi d'Yvetot. / ADAM, ADOLPHE CHARLES (1803-1856), MLM 5
  "Opéra comique en 3 actes. Paroles de MM. de Leuven et Brunswick. Musique de Ad. Adam. Partition piano et chant...Paris, J. Meissonier [ca. 1843] P1. no. J. M. 1770 First edition. inscribed by the composer, with numerous corrections in his hand on p. 74-77. Wotquenne, 2515.
- Le Torcador ou L'accord Paufait / ADAM, ADOLPHE CHARLES (1803-1856), MLM 5A.
  1849. Caqliostra
- Pepita Jiménez. / ALBENIZ ISAAC MANUEL FRANCISCO (1860-1909), MLM 6
  "A lyric comedy in two acts and three tableaux (from the novel by Juan Valera) ... by F. B. Money-Coutts. Deutsche Bearbeitung von 0. Berggruen. Music by I. Albéniz. Mit deutschem und englischem Text....Klavierauszug mit Text von Componisten. Leipzig, Breitkopf & Härtel, C1896. P1. no. 21596. First edition. Presented for the first time at Barcelona, January 5, 1896.
- Iberia / ALBENIZ ISAAC MANUEL FRANCISCO (1860-1909), MLM 6A.
  "Iberia. 12 nouvelles 'impressions"" en quatre cahiers. (ler cahier) Evocation, El puerto, Fete-Fieu a Seville. Transcription à 4 mains. Paris, Edition Muteelle, ca. 1906. 33p. 35 cm. Inscribed by the composer.
- VIII sonate per cembalo. / ALBERTI, DOMENICO (1710-1740), MLM 7
  "Opera prima da Domenico Alberti. London, I. Walsh [ca. 1750] First edition. Wolffheim,I, 1214.
- L'ombra di Don Giovanni. / ALFANO, FRANCO (1876- ), MLM 8
  "Dramma lirico in tre atti e quattro quadri di Ettore Moschino. Musica di Franco Alfano. Opera completa per canto e piano-forte. Riduzione dell'autore. Milano, G. Ricordi, c1914. P1. no. 114972. First edition.
- Sinfonia. / ARDITI, LUIGI (1822-1903), MLM 9
  "Original manuscript. 1841. 30 leaves (title-page, 58 pages) 22 x 32 1/2 cm. This is an overture and not a symphony as the title indicates. Arditi, who spent some time as a conductor in New York City, is remembered for his lilting waltz, ""Il bacio.""
- [Inserted program] / ARDITI, LUIGI (1822-1903), MLM 9A
- The favourite songs in the opera called Coriolanus. / ARIOSTI, ATTILIO (1666-1740), MLM 10
  "London, I. Walsh [1723] First edition.
- [A collection of songs] / ARNE, MICHAEL (1741-1786), MLM 11
  "A collection of favourite songs which were sung by Mrs. Arne at Ranelagh and Vauxhall, never before publish'd, with the new Scots ballad Pitty Patty, now sung by Mrs. Weichsel at Vauxhall, composed by Michael Arne. London, C. and S. Thompson [1775] First edition. Signed by the composer.
- [The music in The judgment of Paris.] / ARNE, THOMAS AUGUSTINE (1710-1778), MLM 12
  "The music in The judgment of Paris. Consisting of all the songs, duettos and trio, with the overture in score as perform'd at the Theatre Royal in Drury Lane. To which are added the celebrated ode, in honour of Great Britain, call'd Rule Britannia, and Sawney & Jenney, a favourite dialogue, in ye Scotch stile. The whole compos'd by Thomas Augustine Arne. Opera sesta. London, Henry Waylett [1741] First edition. The text of The judgment of Paris is by Congreve. Rule Britannia 'Was performed for the first time in the masque of Alfred at Cliefden, the residence of Frederick, Prince of Wales, August 1, 1740. The judgment of Paris was also first performed at Cliefden the same year. When the latter was published in 1741, the music of ""Rule Britannia"" was added as an appendix. The music of Alfred was not published until 1751. The words by James Thomson were published separately three weeks after the performance. ""It is just possible that the ascription to Thomson is incorrect as he had a partner in the writing of the masque, the dramatist David Mallet or Malloch (ca. 1705-1765), but it is thought that the particular song was Thomson's because its sentiment had already appeared in two poems of his and seems to be a personal specialty."" The Oxford companion to music, by Percy A. Scholes. London, Oxford University Press, 1947, p. 818.
- Mazurka des traineaux. / ASCHER, JOSEPH (1829-1869), MLM 13
  "Orchestrée par Georges Bizét. Paris, H. Lemoine, Ca. 1860. Proof-sheets: p. 2, 5, 6, 8, 10, II, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16 and their conjugates p. 30, 28, 27, 25, 23, 22, 21, 20, 19, 18, 17 are on blank sheets; p. 3, 4, 7 and their conjugates p. 30, 29, 26 are on sheets one side of which has in each instance been used for the proof of one page of an unidentified piano composition with the plate number 7418 H; p.9 and its conjugate p. 24 is on a sheet one side of which has been used for the proof of one page of another unidentified piano composition with the plate number 7397 P, 299 H. This is the first proof with Bizet's corrections. The first page (blank) has a note: ""Ir épreuve faire une 2e épreuve. G. Bizet"" There is a penciled note in another hand on the same page: Published by H. Lemoine. Page 2 has a penciled note in still another hand: ""Ascher: Mazurka des Traineaux. Orchestrée par Georges Bizet."" The pages with plate numbers 7418 H and 7397 P, 299 H have manuscript corrections.
- ATTWOOD, THOMAS (1765-1838) See BISHOP, Sir HENRY Rowley (1786-1855) Guy Mannering.
- Andante. / AUBER, DANIEL FRANCOIS ESPRIT (1782-1871), MLM 14
  "Original manuscript signed. 2 leaves (3 pages) 27 X 35-1/2 cm. Piano and vocal score. The text begins: "Quel pouvoir peut è cette fête hélas m'entrainer malgré moi."
- [Postcard] / AUBER, DANIEL FRANCOIS ESPRIT (1782-1871), MLM 14A
  postcard
- La bergère châtelaine. / AUBER, DANIEL FRANCOIS ESPRIT (1782-1871), MLM 15
  "Opéra en trois actes, représenté pour la première fois sur le Théâtre Royal de l'Opéra Comique, le 27 janvier 1820. Paroles de Monsieur Planard, mis en musique et dédié à Monsieur Cherubini. par D. F. E. Auber. Paris, Ph. Petit [1820] P1. no. 3. First edition. Inscribed to Zimmerman by the composer. Orchestral score. Wotquenne, 1328.
- [Portrait] / AUBER, DANIEL FRANCOIS ESPRIT (1782-1871), MLM 15A
  Engraved portrait of the composer by Julien.
- La fiancée. / AUBER, DANIEL FRANCOIS ESPRIT (1782-1871), MLM 16
  "Opéra comique en trois actes. Paroles de Mr. E. Scribe. Musique de D. F. E. Auber. Partition piano et chant. Paris, G. Brandus et S. Dufour [ca. 1850] P1. no. T. 1408. At head of title: ""Nouvelle edition."" Inscribed by the composer. Presented for the first time at Paris, January 10, 1829. Wotquenne, 2538.
- [Leocadie] / AUBER, DANIEL FRANCOIS ESPRIT (1782-1871), MLM 17
  "Morceaux de Léocadie arrangés pour le piano. Paris, Ignace Pleyel [ca. 1824] P1. nos. 743 A-G. Caption-title. First edition. The text is by MM. Scribe and Melesville. Presented for the first time at Paris, November 4, 1824
- La muette de Portici. / AUBER, DANIEL FRANCOIS ESPRIT (1782-1871), MLM 18
  "Opéra en cinq actes. Paroles de MM. Scribe et Germain Delavigne. Composé et arrangé pour le piano forte par D. F. E. Auber...Paris, Maurice Schlesinger [1828] P1. no. 328. First edition. Also known as Masaniello. Presented for the first time at Paris, February 29, 1828. Inserted is an autograph letter signed. To an unknown correspondent, declining an invitation, n. p., dated ""9 janvier.""
- Le testament et les billets doux / AUBER, DANIEL FRANCOIS ESPRIT (1782-1871), MLM 19
  "Opéra comique en un acte, paroles de Mr. Planard, musique de D. F. E. Auber. ... Paris, Ph. Petit [1819] P1. no. 2. First edition. Inscribed to Zimmerman by the composer. Orchestral score. Presented for the first time at Paris, September 18, 1819. Wotquenne, 1327.
- [Autograph] / AUBER, DANIEL FRANCOIS ESPRIT (1782-1871), MLM 19A
  "Inserted is an autograph note signed to M. Berard, n. p., dated ""Décembre 3""
- La forêt bleue. / AUBERT, LOUIS (1877-), MLM 20
  "Conte Iyrique en 3 actes (d'après les contes de Perrault). Poème de Jacques Chenevière. Musique de Louis Aubert. Partition chant et piano avec textes français et anglais. Traduction anglaise par Hermann Klein. Paris, A. Durand & Fils, c1911. P1. no. 7414. First edition. Inscribed to Archaimbaud, chef des choeurs at the Paris première, June 1924, by the composer and Jacques Chenevière. Presented for the first time at Boston, December 1911.
- Serment d'amour. / AUDRAN, EDMOND (1840-1901), MLM 21
  "Opéra-comique en 3 actes de Maurice Ordonneau. Musique de Ed. Audran. Partition chant & piano transcrite par Marius Baggers. Paris, Choudens Père & Fils [1886]P1. no. A.C. 7132. First edition. Inscribed by the composer. Presented for the first time at Paris, February 19, 1886.
- L'éventail de Jeanne. / AURIC, GEORGES (1899-) See RAVEL, MAURICE JOSEPH (1875-1937)
- "Six concerti pour le clavecin, deux violons & une violoncelle. " / BACH, JOHANN CHRISTIAN (1735-1782), MLM 22
  "Très humblement dédiés à sa majesté Charlotte, reine de la Grande Bretagne ... Composés par Jean Bach. Oevre premier [Oeuvre première] Londres, Welcker [ca. 1763]. Separate parts.
- "[Suite in F major] Four dances: Allemanda,Courante, Sarabande and Gigue. " / BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 23
  "Original manuscript unsigned. ca. 1705-1706. 2 leaves (4pages) 19 1/2 x 33 cm. Written on paper with the water mark: D.H. This is one of the earliest existing manuscripts of Bach. It was discovered by Manfred Gorke in 1929 and played for the first time after its discovery, May 25, 1930, at the Kreuzkirche in Dresden by Rudolph Mauersberger. Cf. Gorke, Manfred. ""Suite in F-dur. Autograph Johann Sebastian Bach.""
- [Ich liebe den Höchsten] / "BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 24
  "Original manuscript signed. 1 leaf (2 pages) 22x32 1/2 cm. Inserted is a letter dated August 1, 1901, to Sir Edward Speyer from Dr. A. Kopfermann of the Royal Library, Berlin, in which this cantata is referred to as follows: ""The Royal Library possesses the autograph score of this, but of the autograph parts only those of the organ, 1st and 2nd violin and viola. Your own bass air is therefore, as you will see, the one missing in our parts."" Also inserted is an autograph letter of Sir Donald Francis Tovey to Sir Edward Speyer, July 31, 1901, referring to this manuscript and other musical matters. Bach-Gesellschaft, XVIII, no. 174.
- [Magnificat] / "BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 25
  "Magnificat a cinque voci, due violini, due oboe, tre trombi, tamburi, basson, viola e basso continuo, del Sigl. J. S. Bach ... Bonn, N. Simrock [ca. 1811] Pl. no. 770. First edition. Bach's Magnificat is one of his most masterly creations. It was composed for performance at Christmas, 1723, the first year of his cantorship at Leipzig. In its original form (E-flat major) it was interspersed, as was customary, with Christmas hymns; but the final form (D major) was without them (cf. Terry, J.S. Bach, 1933, p. 178). Fétis,p. 195.
- [Prel and fugue, organ, S. 544, B minor]" / BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 25A
  Praeludium pro organo cum pedale obligato. (Prel and fugue, organ, S. 544, B minor] [ca.1730. Cambridge, Heffner, 1943] fascim. ([10] p.). [2] p. 29cm. (The Harrow replicas, no.4) Imprint on label mounted On fly-leaf. Facsim. of the composer's ms. in the collection Mrs. Gisella Selden-Goth, New~ York. J.S.Bach's Prelude and fugue in B minor, bv O.E.Deutsch ([2] p.at end)
- [Koffeekantate] / BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 25B
- Grosse Passionsmusik nach dem Evangelium Matthaei von Johann Sebastian Bach. / BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 26
  Volständiger Klavierauszug von Adolph Bernhard Marx ... Berlin, Schlesinger, 1830. Pl. no. 1571. First edition. Bach's great St. Matthew Passion, published for subscribers only, was composed for Good Friday, 1729, but remained in manuscript for a hundred years. It was eventually published as a result of the enthusiasm aroused by its performance under Mendelssohn in 1829. Hirsch, IV, 1136; Wotquenne,714.
- [Engraved portrait of the composer] / BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 26A
  Engraved portrait of the composer by F. W. Meyer after L. Wolf.
- The favourite songs in the opera Orfeo. / BACH, JOHANN CHRISTIAN (1735-1782), MLM 27
  London, R. Bremner [1770] First edition. This is the first collection including three arias by Bach and five by Gluck. First edition of Bach's contributions and first English edition of Gluck's. Libretto by Bottarelli. Unknown to Wotquenne. From the Library of the Earl of Aylesford.
- 371 vierstimmige Choralgesänge von Johann Sebastian Bach. / BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 28
  Dritte Auflage...Leipzig, Breitkopf & Härtel [1831] P1. no. 5089. Although called the third edition, strictly speaking this is the fourth, as 200 of the Chorales first appeared in 1765 and 1769. The second edition, which was the first to contain the 371 appeared in 1785-1787 in four volumes and the third in 1804. Cf. Hirsch, 111,42-43. V
- Sheep may safely graze. / BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 28A
  John Barbirolli
- Where the bee sucks / BACH, JOHANN SEBASTIAN (1685-1750), MLM 28B
  Ernst Bacon
- / Bache, D.F.E. - see Additions., MLM 28.3A
- Rêverie pour le piano par Mili Balakirew. / BALAKIREFF, MILY ALEXEIVICH (1837-1910), MLM 29
  Manuscript signed. April 10, 1903. 5 leaves (7 pages) 26 1/2 x36cm. The first page has a discarded version of that Part of the score which appears on the second page. A manuscript title-page in the composer's handwriting is pasted over this. This includes a dedication: ""A Monsieur Serge Trailine"" Between the fifth and eighth pages numbered in the manuscript ""5"" and ""6"" are two unnumbered pages on the first of which are six bars of music - a discarded version corresponding to a part of the score on the third page of the manuscript. The plate number Z3886 is written in at the bottom of the second page. A penciled note on the title indicates that the score was to be published by Zimmermann, St. Petersburg. From the collection of Michael D. Calvocoressi.
- Russia. / BALAKIREFF, MILY ALEXEIVICH (1837-1910), MLM 30
  Poëme symphonique pour orchestre par M. Balakirew ...St. Petersbourg, W. Bessel [1893] P1. no. 2688. Cover-title. Title-page in Russian. Second edition. Inscribed to Louis Albert Bourgault-Ducoudray by the composer.
- The Bohemian girl / BALFE, MICHAEL WILLIAM (1808-1870), MLM 31
  The Bohemian girl, a grand opera in three acts, as performed at the Theatre Royal, Drury Lane. Written by Alfred Bunn, Esqre. Composed and dedicated to Val. Morris, Junr., Esqre, by M. W. Balfe...London, Chappell [1843] P1. nos. 6753, 6798, 6743, 6780, 6757, 6752, 6809, 6751, 6809, 6742, 6764, 6797, 6747, 6746, 6799, 6814, 6803, 6859, 6754, 6810, 6767, 6810, 6783, 6763, 6784, 6779. First edition. Piano and vocal score. Presented for the first time at London, November 27, 1843. This opera, the first by a native British composer to acquire international fame, includes two songs that are familiar wherever English is spoken: ""I dreamt that I dwelt in marble halls"" and ""When other lips,"" better known as ""You'll remember me."" Inserted are the original manuscript of Balfe's ""The young soldier"" (cf. separate entry), and an autograph letter signed by Sir Robert Stewart, written to Dr. Frazer relating to this composition.
- Les quatre fils Aymon. / BALFE, MICHAEL WILLIAM (1808-1870), MLM 32
  Opéra comique en 3 actes. Paroles de MM. de Leuven et Brunswick. Musique de M. W. Balfe...Paris, Choudens [ca. 1845] P1. no. C. 46. First edition. Piano and vocal score. Presented for the first time at Paris, July 15, 1844.
- The young soldier. / BALFE, MICHAEL WILLIAM (1808-1870), MLM 33
  Original manuscript signed. Ca. 1837. 4 leaves (6 pages) 23 x 30 1/2 cm. The words are by Edward Fitzball. Inserted in Balfe's The Bohemian girl.
- Satanella / BALFE, MICHAEL WILLIAM (1808-1870), MLM 33A.
- Mon ami Pierrot. / BARLOW, SAMUEL L. M. (1892- ), MLM 34
  Légende musicale en un acte. Paroles de Sacha Guitry. Musique de S. Barlow...Partition piano et chant réduite par l'auteur...Paris, Choudens [c1924] P1. no. A. C. 17546. First edition. inscribed to Nix [N. de Molas?] by the composer.
- Achille all-assedio di Troja. / BASILY, FRANCESCO (1767-1850), MLM 35
  Original manuscript. 1798. 212 leaves (422 pages) 161/2 x 111/2 cm. The manuscript, written with the greatest care and exactness, offers a very instructive example of the opera seria cultivated in Italy at the close of the 18th century. Basily held two of the most important official positions of the Church in Italy: he was maestro di capella in Loreto and of St. Peter's in Rome. As director of the conservatory in Milan from 1827 till 1837, he was a teacher of Glinka and refused Verdi admission to the conservatory. Achille is a three-act opera following the pattern of the opera seria prior to Gluck. It contains twelve arias, three duettos and two quartettos with fourteen secco and eight accompagnato recitatives and two marches in between. The opera is scored for two flutes, oboes, clarinets, bassoons, horns, trumpets, and the customary strings. There are no chorus numbers and broad finales. A terzetto concludes the first act, a quartetto the second and a quintetto the short third act. The calligraphic make-up and the layout of this manuscript are an astounding achievement in view of the small size of the music paper and the by no means small orchestral apparatus which often required nine staves.
- Third symphony / BAX, SIR ARNOLD TREVOR (1883- ), MLM 36
  [by] Arnold Bax. [London] Murdoch, Murdoch, c1931. P1. no. M. M. & Co. 555. Page-proofs with corrections and changes throughout in the composer's hand. Orchestral score. Presented for the first time at London, March 4, 1930, under the direction of Sir Henry Wood, to whom the symphony is dedicated.
- / Bazin, F. - See Additions., MLM 36T
- [Autograph letter signed.] / BEAUMARCHAIS, PIERRE AUGUSTIN (1732-1799), MLM 37
  To Mme. Pankouke. [November 22, 1779]. 4 leaves (3 pages) 19 x 23cm. Rossini's Il barbiere di Siviglia with libretto by Sterbini is founded on Beaumarchais' comedy: Le barbier de Seville. An interesting letter in response to one sent to him in which he apparently had been asked to recall a composition he had played on some social occasion many years previously. He expresses his regret that he is unable to recall it. Inserted in first edition of Rossini's Il barbiere di Siviglia, Rome, ca. 1817.
- In questa tomba oscura. / BEETHOVEN, LUDWIG VAN (1770-1827), MLM 38
  Arietta con accompagnamento di piano-forte composta in diverse maniere da molti autori e dedicata a S. A. U. Sig. Principe Giuseppe di Lobkowitz...Vienna, T. Mollo [1808] P1. no. M. 1487. First edition. The text is by Giuseppe Antonio Carpani (1752-1825). The work contains sixty-three versions by various composers of which Beethoven's is the last - LXIII, p. 201-203. Saint-Saëns' copy with his signature on front wrapper. Grove, 239. Original manuscript of Beethoven's In questa tomba oscura. (cf. separate entry) and a holograph copy of the arietta, signed by Carpani, Vienna, October 19, 1812.
- In questa tomba oscura. / BEETHOVEN, LUDWIG VAN (1770-1827), MLM 39
  Original manuscript unsigned. 1807. 2 leaves (4 pages) 32 x 23 -1/2 cm. Corrections in red pencil. First edition of in questa tomba oscura.
- In questa tomba oscura. / BEETHOVEN, LUDWIG VAN (1770-1827), MLM 39A
  Photographs of manuscript in Robert O. Lehman's collection on deposit in the Morgan Library.
- / BEETHOVEN, LUDWIG VAN (1770-1827), MLM 39B
- Andenken von Matthison in Musik gesetzr von Louis van Beethoven. / BEETHOVEN, LUDWIG VAN (1770-1827), MLM 40
  Leipzig, Breitkopf & Härtel [1810] P1. no. 1526. First edition. Grove, 240; Hirsch, IV, 460; Nottebohm, p. 180.
- [Concerto, D major, opus 61] " / BEETHOVEN, LUDWIG VAN (1770-1827), MLM 41
  Collection complète des sept concertos et d'une fantaisie pour piano, orchestre et choeur de L. van Beethoven pour piano et orchestre. Mis en partition par Henri Roubier...Paris, S. Richault [ca. 1857] P1.no.7813.R. This volume contains only the score for the sixth concerto with the caption title: 6ème concerto in ré maj. Op. 61. First edition. The instrumental parts were published in 1808 (cf. Hirsch, IV, 301). The concerto was composed and performed for the first time in 1806. Nottebohm, p. 58.
- [Elegischer Gesange, opus 118] " / BEETHOVEN, LUDWIG VAN (1770-1827), MLM 42